

Lucas Daniel Lo Vercio, Ph.D.

POSTDOCTORAL ASSOCIATE

Department of Cell Biology & Anatomy, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada
☐ +1 403-923-9735 | ■ lucaslovercio@gmail.com | ♣

https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Lucas_Lo_Vercio | • https://github.com/lucaslovercio/ | • https://www.linkedin.com/in/lucas-lo-vercio/

Summary ___

I was born in Quilmes, Argentina, on May 12, 1987. I am a computer scientist with a strong background in mathematics. My research fields are medical and biological images analysis and machine learning. Currently, I am researching on automatic segmentation, registration and quantification of microscopy images using deep learning. Previously, I worked on the automatic analysis of a variety of ultrasound images (IVUS, carotid ultrasound) for clinical research, diagnosis and training. I am highly experienced in university-level teaching and mentoring in systems engineering. I consider myself a problem-solving professional in data science and imaging.

Education

Universidad Nacional del Centro de la Provincia de Buenos Aires (UNCPBA)

Tandil, Argentina 2012-2017

PhD in Computational and Industrial Mathematics.

- Thesis Title: Feature engineering and machine learning for intravascular ultrasound segmentation.
- Supervisors: Dr. Ignacio Larrabide and Dr. Mariana del Fresno (PLADEMA Research Institute).

UNCPBA Tandil, Argentina
Systems Engineer 2005-2011

- Final project title: Multiresolution visulization of topographic meshes.
- Supervisors: Dr. Alejandro Clausse and Msc. Virginia Cifuentes (PLADEMA Research Institute).

OTHER CERTIFICATIONS AND COURSES

- 2018 Argentina National Space Activities Commission (CONAE), Level 2: Introduction to SAR remote sensing
- **2017 CONAE**, Introduction to Geospatial Technologies in Agriculture
- **2016 CONAE**, SoPI I: Introduction to Remote Sensing

Current and Past Positions _____

2018-date	Postdoctoral associate, Eyes High Postdoctoral Fellow (2018-2020) , Department of Cell Biology & Anatomy,
2010-uale	University of Calgary, Canada. Supervisors: Dr. Benedikt Hallgrímsson and Dr. Nils Forkert.
2017-2018	Postdoctoral Fellow, National Scientific and Technical Research Council (CONICET), PLADEMA-UNCPBA.
2017-2016	Argentina
2012-2017	PhD Fellow, National Scientific and Technical Research Council (CONICET), PLADEMA-UNCPBA. Argentina
2012-2019	Graduate Teaching Assistant, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, UNCPBA, Argentina
2011-2012	Software Developer, UNITECH S.A., Buenos Aires, Argentina
2009-2012	Undergraduate Teaching Assistant, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, UNCPBA, Argentina

Technical Knowledge_

Medical Image Processing: Intravascular Ultrasound (IVUS), Common Carotid Artery Ultrasound (CCA US), Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT), Computed Tomography (CT), Optical Projection Tomography (OPT), micro-Computed Tomography (micro-CT), Light-Sheet Microscopy (LSFM).

Programming Languages: C/C++, Python, Java; MATLAB; SQL.

Machine Learning: SVMs, Random Forests, CNNs, GANs.

Developer Tools: Microsoft Visual Studio; Eclipse IDE; MATLAB; IBM Rational Software Architect; Paraview, 3DSlicer, Py-Charm.

R&D Projects _____

The role of continuous phenotypic variation in structural defects of the face. National Institute of Health (NIH NIDCR R01-DE019638). 2022-2023. Personnel.

A3SIS: Machine learning for detection and classification in satellite images. Ministry of Defense (Argentina). PIDDEF 12/16. 2017-2019. Director/Vice director.

HI-MED - Computational tools for image quantification, simulation and planning of treatments in medicine. MINCyT-ANPCyT (Argentina). PICT 2016-0116. 2017-2018. Personnel.

Imaging and simulation for diagnosis and treatment of vascular diseases. MINCyT-ANPCyT (Argentina). PICT 2014-1730. 2015-2017. Personnel.

SIMECO - Ultrasound simulator for medical training. PDTS-PCTI-158, Ministry of Science, Technology and Innovation (Argentina). 2014. Consultant - programmer.

Teaching Experience _____

	2023	MDSC 689.11 - Medical Imaging Applications, Guest lecturer. Topics: Image registration,	UCalgary
		Machine Learning.	o oa.ga.y
	2022	Workshop: Introduction to Image Processing using Open-Source Software, Instructor.	UCalgary
	2022	Topics: Filtering. Segmentation. 3DSlicer, Paraview, ITK, Python.	Ocalgary
	2018	Technological Applications for Conservation, Instructor. Topics: GPS, Geographic	UNCPBA
	2010	Information Systems, Image Processing.	UNCEDA
	2014, 2015,	Medical Imaging workshop, Teaching Assistant. Topics: Filtering, segmentation,	UNCPBA
	2017	quantification and registration of medical images.	UNCPDA
		Software Development Methodologies I, Teaching Assistant. Topics: UML, UP, Agile	
	2009-2018	software development. IBM Professional Qualification "RT011 - Modeling of	UNCPBA
		Object-Oriented Systems with Rational"	
2016	2016-2018	Information Technologies for Organizations, Teaching Assistant. Topics: Fundamentals of	UNCPBA
	2010-2018	organizations, Business requirements, Git, CMMI.	UNCPDA
0011	2011 2010	Design of Compilers I, Teaching Assistant. Topics: Symbols tables, lexical and syntactic	LINCODA
2011-2	2011-2019	analysis, YACC, Assembly language.	UNCPBA
		Data Storage Structures, Teaching Assistant. Topics: Data modeling (Entity-Relationship	
	2011	Diagrams, Normal Forms, Business Requirements) and data structures in secondary	UNCPBA
		storage.	

Mentoring____

2021	Co-Supervisor of Honours thesis for the Bachelor in Health Sciences, One (1) student	UCalgary
2020-2021	Co-Supervisor of Summer Studentships, Two (2) students	UCalgary
2017-2020	Supervisor of Final Projects for the degree in Systems Engineer, Four (4) students	UNCPBA
2017-2018	Supervisor of Research Student Fellowships, Two (2) students	UNCPBA

Awards, Fellowships, & Grants _____

2015 Student Scholarship to attend to CARS 2015, International Society for Computer Aided €1,000

2017-2018 Post-Doctoral Fellowship, CONICET

2012-2017 Doctoral Fellowship, CONICET

2007 **2nd Place - Student project**, Jornadas Argentinas de Informática.

Scientific Community _____

2017-date

Reviewer, Journals: Ultrasonics, Computers in Biology and Medicine, Medical Physics, BioMedical Engineering OnLine, Methods in Ecology and Evolution, International Journal for Numerical Methods in Biomedical

Engineering, Physics in Medicine and Biology, Ultrasonic Imaging, Journal of Neural Engineering, GigaScience,

Medical Image Analysis.

2021-date Member, Red de Científicos Argentinos en Canadá

Session Chair: Computer Vision, VI Congreso de Matemática Aplicada, Computacional e Industrial. Comodoro Rivadavia, Argentina

Local organizing committee member. Student Poster Session Organizer., 12th International Symposium on

Medical Information Processing and Analysis (SIPAIM 2016). Tandil, Argentina

2009 Local organizing committee member, XVIII Congreso sobre métodos numéricos y sus aplicaciones. Tandil, Argentina

Departamental Services _____

2021	Judge, McCaig Institute Summer Student Symposium, University of Calgary, Canada
2019-2020,	
2021-2022	
2015-2018	Member of various Teaching Assistant selection committees, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, UNCPBA, Argentina
2015-2017	Member of various Final Project evaluation committees, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, UNCPBA, Argentina

Languages _____

Spanish

NATIVE LANGUAGE

English

CELPIP (OCTOBER 2022)

Publications _____

PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL ARTICLES

- **Lucas D. Lo Vercio**, Rebecca M. Green, Samuel Robertson, Sienna Guo, Andreas Dauter, Marta Marchini, Marta Vidal-García, Xiang Zhao, Anandita Mahika, Ralph S. Marcucio, Benedikt Hallgrímsson, Nils D. Forkert. *Segmentation of Tissues and Proliferating Cells in Light-Sheet Microscopy Images of Mouse Embryos Using Convolutional Neural Networks.* IEEE Access. 2022; 11, 105084-105100.
- Jay Devine, Marta Vidal-García, Wei Liu, Amanda Neves, **Lucas D. Lo Vercio**, Rebecca M. Green, Heather A. Richbourg, Marta Marchini, et al. *MusMorph, a database of standardized mouse morphology data for morphometric meta-analyses.* Scientific Data. 2022.
- Nicolas Toussaint, Yushi Redhead, Marta Vidal-García, **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Wei Liu, Elizabeth M. C. Fisher, Benedikt Hallgrímsson, Victor L. J. Tybulewicz, Julia A. Schnabel, Jeremy B. A. Green. *A landmark-free morphometrics pipeline for high-resolution phenotyping: application to a mouse model of Down syndrome*. Development. 2021; 148 (18).

- Marta Marchini, Diane Hu, **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Nathan M. Young, Nils D. Forkert, Benedikt Hallgrímsson, Ralph Marcucio. *Wnt Signaling Drives Correlated Changes in Facial Morphology and Brain Shape*. Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology. 2021.
- Jay Devine, Jose D. Aponte, David C. Katz, Wei Liu, **Lucas D. Lo Vercio**, Nils D. Forkert, Ralph Marcucio, Christopher J. Percival, Benedikt Hallgrímsson. *A Registration and Deep Learning Approach to Automated Landmark Detection for Geometric Morphometrics*. Evolutionary Biology. 2020; 47, 246–259.
- **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Mariana del Fresno, Ignacio Larrabide. *Lumen-intima and media-adventitia segmentation in IVUS images using supervised classifications of arterial layers and morphological structures.* Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine. 2019. 177, 113-121.
- Hugo Luis Manterola, **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Alejandro Díaz, Mariana del Fresno, Ignacio Larrabide. *Validation of an Open-Source Tool for Measuring Carotid Lumen Diameter and Intima–Media Thickness*. Ultrasound in Medicine & Biology. 2018. 44 (8), 1873-1881.
- Alejandro Diaz, Daniel Bia, Yanina Zócalo, Hugo Manterola, Ignacio Larrabide, **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Mariana Del Fresno, Edmundo Cabrera Fischer. *Carotid Intima Media Thickness Reference Intervals for a Healthy Argentinean Population Aged* 11–81 Years. International Journal of Hypertension. 2018.
- **Lucas Lo Vercio**, José Ignacio Orlando, Mariana del Fresno, Ignacio Larrabide. *Assessment of image features for vessel wall segmentation in intravascular ultrasound images*. International Journal of Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery. 2016. 11, 1397–1407.

TUTORIALS AND LITERATURE REVIEWS

Lucas Lo Vercio, Kimberly Amador, Jordan J. Bannister, Sebastian Crites, Alejandro Gutierrez, M. Ethan MacDonald, Jasmine Moore, Pauline Mouches, Deepthi Rajashekar, Serena Schimert, Nagesh Subbanna, Anup Tuladhar, Nanjia Wang, Matthias Wilms, Anthony Winder, Nils D. Forkert. *Supervised machine learning tools: a tutorial for clinicians*. Journal of Neural Engineering. 2020; 17 (6).

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PAPERS

- **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Mariana Del Fresno, Ignacio Larrabide. *Detection of morphological structures for vessel wall segmentation in IVUS using random forests.* Proc. SPIE 10160, 12th International Symposium on Medical Information Processing and Analysis. 2017.
- Hugo Luis Manterola, **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Alejandro Díaz, Pamela Alejandra Pardini, María Victoria Waks Serra, Mariana del Fresno, Ignacio Larrabide. *Low-cost phantoms for validating measurements in ultrasound vascular images.* Proc. SPIE 10160, 12th International Symposium on Medical Information Processing and Analysis. 2017.
- Juan P. D'Amato, **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Pablo Rubi, Ezequiel Fernandez Vera, Rosana Barbuzza, Mariana Del Fresno, Ignacio Larrabide. *Efficient scatter model for simulation of ultrasound images from computed tomography data.* Proc. SPIE 9681, 11th International Symposium on Medical Information Processing and Analysis. 2015.
- **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Javier Dottori, Ignacio Larrabide, Jose Luis Díez-Gil, Mariana del Fresno, Pablo Lotito. *Guidewire artifact tracking on IVUS*. V MACI. Tandil, Buenos Aires, Argentina. 2015.
- Hugo Manterola, **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Mariana del Fresno. *Reducing Artifacts Impact on IVUS Automatic Segmentation Via Inpainting*. Mecánica Computacional. 2014. 33 (41).

Presentations_

CONFERENCE TALKS

Conference Papers mentioned before were presented, but omitted here. * presenting author; * mentored undergraduate

- **Lucas Lo Vercio***, Rebecca Green, Andreas Dauter, Elizabeth Barretto, Marta Marchini, Marta Vidal-García, Samuel Robertson, Anandita Mahika, Alejandro Gutierrez, Sienna Guo, Xiang Zhao, Ralph Marcucio, Nils Forkert, Benedikt Hallgrímsson. *Deep Learning for Automatic Analysis of Light-Sheet Microscopy Images of Mouse Embryos.* Poster. 8th Meeting of the European Society for Evolutionary Developmental Biology. May 2022. Napoli, Italy.
- Rebecca M. Green^{*}, **Lucas Lo Vercio**, Sienna Guo, Andreas Dauter, Marta Marchini, Xiang Xhao, Ralph S. Marcucio, Benedikt Hallgrímsson. *Mapping the relationship between proliferation and morphology in the developing mouse face.* Experimental Biology. April 2020. Virtual.

- Carolina Bruscantini^{+,*}, **Lucas D. Lo Vercio**, Pablo Rinaldi. *Correction of Digital Elevation Models based on Radar, using Land-sat Imagery and Machine Learning.* Lecture Presentation. XII Argentinian Congress of Agroinformatics (CAI 2020). 2020. La Plata, Argentina.
- Eugenia Moris^{+,*}, **Lucas D. Lo Vercio**, Ignacio Larrabide. *Automatic detection of morphological structures in Intravascular Ultrasound images with Convolutional Neural Network.* Lecture Presentation. Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery Congress. 2019. Rennes, France.
- **Lucas Lo Vercio***, José Ignacio Orlando, Mariana del Fresno, Ignacio Larrabide. *Assessment of image features for vessel wall segmentation in intravascular ultrasound images.* Poster and short presentation. Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery Congress. 2015. Barcelona, Spain.

INVITED TALKS

- May 2018. *Machine Learning for Image Processing*. Invited talk: 1st Workshop Red argentina de neuroimágenes y mapeo cerebral. Florencio Varela, Argentina.
- June 2017. Computer-aided diagnosis using ultrasound imaging. Invited talk: Post-secondary Education, Science and Technology. Coronel Vidal, Argentina.